Preliminary Guide to the Neal E. Miller Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Neal E. Miller papers
1926-2000
MS 1770
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
59.5
(61 boxes)
The papers include personal and professional correspondence, organizational files, course materials, writings, grant files, and audiovisual materials which document Neal Miller's work in psychology. The papers highlight Miller's research in visceral learning and behavioral medicine and his work with professional organizations, such as the Society for Neuroscience, the Biofeedback Society of America, the Academy of Behavioral Medicine Research, the President's Science Advisory Committee, and the Advisory Committee on Animals in research. The papers include extensive files on the debate over the moral and ethical aspects of animal experimentation.
Miller, Neal E. (Neal Elgar), 1909-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Neal E. Miller, 2000, and the estate of Neal E. Miller, 2003. Transferred from the Dept. of Psychology, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
These records are available for research, with the exception of unprocessed materials, which are closed until processed.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Neal Miller was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin on August 3, 1909. He received a B.S. from the University of Washington in 1931, an M.A. from Stanford University in 1932, and a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1935. He served as a research assistant and research associate in psychology at Yale before earning the rank of professor in 1950. From 1966 until 1980, he served as a professor at Rockefeller University. In his research, Miller explored ways in which learning theory could be employed to understand problems of human behavior and psychopathology. A pioneer in the field of behavioral medicine, Miller studied the effects of learning on visceral responses and the effects of stress on the immune system. He was prominent in advocating animal research. Miller died March 23, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The papers include personal and professional correspondence, organizational files, course materials, writings, grant files, and audiovisual materials which document Neal Miller's work in psychology. The papers highlight Miller's research in visceral learning and behavioral medicine and his work with professional organizations, such as the Society for Neuroscience, the Biofeedback Society of America, the Academy of Behavioral Medicine Research, the President's Science Advisory Committee, and the Advisory Committee on Animals in research. The papers include extensive files on the debate over the moral and ethical aspects of animal experimentation.
Animal experimentation -- Moral and ethical aspects; Animal rights -- Moral and ethical aspects; Biological control systems; Learning, Psychology of; Medicine and psychology; Psychology; Social psychology; Miller, Neal E. (Neal Elgar), 1909-2002; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Academy of Behavioral Medicine Research, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol, Drug Abuse, Mental Health Administration Retreat - NIMH, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Aldine Publishing Company[Biofeedback Annual], 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Aldine Annual, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Aldine - Atherton [Shareholders meeting] (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - J. Flanagan, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research, Stress, 1955-1958 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - J. Flanagan, 1948-1955 (Box 1)
  - Air Force POW Project - Corr. Melton, Pattishall (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - Stress Project, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - Project A-85, 1954 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research correspondence 1959, 1959-1971 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - Technical Notes, 1952-1957 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research - Tests for Combat Arms Project, 1955 (Box 1)
  - American Institute for Research Report [Research on behavior impairment] - Draft copy and Miller's review, 1957 (Box 1)
  - American Association For the Advancement of Science 1965, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - American Association For the Advancement of Science Symposium 1956 -Non-technical Abstract of Miller, NEM lecture (Box 1)
  - American Association For the Advancement of Science Press Statements and releases - Dec. 1956 (Box 1)
  - American Association For the Advancement of Science Council, 1979-1983 (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences - 1967, 1967-1983 (Box 1)
  - American Association For the Advancement of Science Bulletin, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education [NEM ms. on televised teaching], 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - American Board of Examiners in Professional Psychology - Questions submitted by NEM, 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Experimental Psychologists, 1959 (Box 1)
  - American College of Neuropsychopharmacology, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - American Heart Association and related correspondence, 1966 (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1968-1984 (Box 1)
  - American Physiological Society, 1964 (Box 1)
  - American Psychological Association
    - Archives (Memo), 1981 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Animal Research and Experimentation [CARE - NEM liaison for NY Academy of Sciences], 1984 (Box 2)
    - Committee on International Relations, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Committee on International Relations, 1967-1972 (Box 2)
    - Clinical Psychologists [list of names, dissertation], 1954 (Box 2)
    - Division 3, 1955-1980 (Box 2)
    - Division 6, 1972-1982 (Box 2)
    - Division 38
      - Awards, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Bylaws, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Chairs, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Continuing Education Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Evaluation, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee '82, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee '79, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - Fellows Committee, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
      - Health Services Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - Journal [Health Psychology, JCCP], 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Scientific Liaison Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - Division Members, 1980-1983 (Box 2)
      - Nominations and Elections, 1981 (Box 2)
      - President [NEM correspondence as Pres.], 1980-1981 (Box 2)
      - President elect [NEM], 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - President past [NEM], 1981-1984 (Box 2)
      - Program, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
      - Program, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
      - Public Info Committee, 1982 (Box 2)
      - Public Policy Committee, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
      - Research Committee, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
      - Training Conference '83, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
      - Women and Health Committee, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Division of School Psychologists [list of members of Committee on Gifted Children], 1956 (Box 2)
    - National Board of Psychological Examiners, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Policy and Planning Board, 1954-1956 (Box 2)
    - Gold Medal Award, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Scientific Awards, 1966-1985 (Box 2)
    - Report on XVIII Congress (Moscow), 1966 (Box 2)
    - Talent Bank, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Div. 38 - Training Conference Funding, 1982 (Box 2)
    - General, 1965-1982 (Box 2)
    - Media Guide (Box 2)
    - "Peace", 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence re USSR, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Task Force on Evaluation of Education, Training and Service in Psychology [bound agenda], 1982 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation of Training, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines [Animal Welfare], 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - Committees: Program, Finance, Local arrangements, 1961-1967 (Box 3)
    - International Congress of Psychology 1963, 1961-1963 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors 1961 --, 1961-1968 (Box 3)
    - General correspondence during Presidency, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Insurance, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Research Support Network, 1980-1985 (Box 3)
    - NSF [National Science Foundation], 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1960 Committee on Scientific Awards (Box 3)
    - Motivation Symposium [International Congress of Psychology], 1963 (Box 3)
  - American Psychological Foundation, 1960-1968 (Box 3)
  - Association for Advancement of Behavior Therapy, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Association for the Advancement of Psychology, 1978 (Box 3)
  - American Psychopathological Association, 1959 (Box 3)
  - AT and T [Behavioral Research], 1981 (Box 3)
  - Audio-Visual Project - Dr. May, etc., 1959 (Box 3)
  - Authorship [grant report] (Box 3)
  - Basic Research - NEM, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Behavioral Medicine [2 articles on behavioral medicine, not NEM], 1979 (Box 3)
  - Behavior Therapy Society, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Behavior Therapy Text [textbooks], 1978 (Box 3)
  - Behavior Immunology Study Group (Harvard), 1983 (Box 3)
  - Behavior Science Council Meeting, Mar. 4-6, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Bell Telephone Feb. 21, 1958 [NEM talk and B.F. Skinner - with Skinner letter signed "Fred"] (Box 3)
  - Biofeedback - American Association of Biofeedback Clinicians (AABC), 1978 (Box 3)
  - Biofeedback - Bibliographies and Researchers (Box 3)
  - Biofeedback Society of NY, 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Biofeedback Therapists [Alan Rappaport], 1974 (Box 3)
    - Relaxation Therapies: An Overview by Alan E. Rappaport, 1974; 1 (Box 3)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Brain Function and Learning: Neurosciences Research Program [Conferences on Learning, 1963, and Brain Function, 1965], 1963, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Brain Function and Learning [Conference at UCLA, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Brain Research Association [Gt. Britain], 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - BBC - Daly ['70], Sabbagh ['72]. Goodwin ['74] [Different programs NEM was on], 1970-1974 (Box 3)
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corp. [NEM on visceral learning], 1973 (Box 3)
  - Carrier Foundation [NEM gave first memorial lecture, was first recipient of award], 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - CBS Conquest -[ Documentary with NEM, "The Brain Story," and text-film "New Frontiers of the Brain"], 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Chemostimulation, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Chile - Rochester Grant Application, 1968 (Box 3)
  - China [NEM trip], 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Chinese Psychologists - Visit '79 [Contains NEM letter to prof in China telling of sending many cartons of his books and journals to China], 1979, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Chinese Visitors 1972 (Box 3)
  - Chlorpromazine [Forward to Swazey book] (Box 3)
  - Clarke, Walter V. Inc. [Professional Advisory Council], 1985 (Box 3)
  - Communications in Behavioral Biology, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Connecticut Mental Health Center, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Connecticut State Psychological Society [Connecticut Psychological Association], 1966 (Box 3)
  - Creative Thinking - Difficulties (Box 3)
  - Creativity booklets, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Council for Advancement of Science Writing [Seminar with NEM], 1966 (Box 3)
  - Cross Cultural Disease Survey - Harvard - NIMH, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Dahl, Lewis K. (Brookhaven Labs), 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Defense Department - Advisory Panel on Psychology and Social Sciences, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Defense Department: Fear and Courage in Training/Combat, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Defense Department: Operations Research [NEM Consultant], 1949-1956 (Box 4)
  - Defense Department: Trip 13th Dec. [NEM on Advisory Panel on Psychology and Social Sciences], 1957 (Box 4)
  - Defense Department:Advisory Panel on Personnel and Training Research [blue booklet, "Fact-Finding Survey..."] (Box 4)
  - Defense Department: Steering Group and Tech. Advisory Panel, 1954-1957 (Box 4)
  - Dollard, John - Consultant [NEM letter to Dollard re work with Ford motor co. on marketing], 1958 (Box 4)
  - Drugs - Correspondence, 1954-1967 (Box 4)
  - Duke University- Ad Hoc Special Training Committee DGMS, 1959-1962 (Box 4)
  - Education: Advisory groups, committees, etc., 1961-1962 (Box 4)
  - Committee for Effective Drug Abuse Legislation, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
  - FBPC (Federation of Behavioral, Psychological, and Cognitive Sciences), 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Frontline (PBS) [re program "Man's Best Friends," on animal rights groups], 1984 (Box 4)
  - NAS Committee on Brain Sciences, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - Adair: Toxin Effects on Fatigue student work [Student work], 1963 (Box 4)
  - Chemostimulation CIBA (Box 4)
  - Chemostimulation - Dosage of Carbachol and Norepinephrine (Box 4)
  - Coons, E..: Notes for Giarman on Brain Stimulation [student work] (Box 4)
  - Curare: Notes, correspondence by Trowill [student work], 1962 (Box 4)
  - Electrodes, Electrode Placement: Coons [student work], 1961 (Box 4)
  - ESB: Inducing Sleep (Box 4)
  - Esophagostomized Rats: Davis [student work], 1963 (Box 4)
  - Fever: Piromen correspondence, etc., 1965 (Box 4)
  - Integrator: Circuit Diagram, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Intragastric Feeding Technique (Box 4)
  - Locusts (and grasshoppers): Importation of.., 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Mouth Fistula Operation: Instructions and correspondence, 1963 (Box 4)
  - NAS Talk (1962) and Materials on Holmes and Gottesman Drug Work (Box 4)
  - Psychopharmacology Drugs: Dosage and Techniques, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Psychopharmacology: Barry, H. [student work], 1962 (Box 4)
  - Research Problems, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - Mimeographed Research Notes, 1957-1960 (Box 4)
  - Norepinephrine: Blocking agents for..., 1964 (Box 4)
  - APA: Symposium on Child Behavior (1957): Spiker, Levin, Miller (Box 4)
  - APA: Publications, Public Relations [incl. brochure on the building of national APA headquarters], 1952 (Box 4)
  - APA: Education and Training Board, 1961 (Box 4)
  - APA: Carter's Symposium [on characteristics of effective fighters], 1954 (Box 4)
  - APA Symposium 1955: Animal Studies Relevant to Psychoanalytic Theory (Box 4)
  - APA: Project A, Style Manual, 1956 (Box 4)
  - APA Talk, Sept. 1957 - Central stimulation and other approaches to motivation and reward [NEM] (Box 4)
  - Berkun, Mitchell - Effect of Amytal on Strength of Pull of Cats [student work], 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Burros, R.H. - Dissertation Experiment 1947-1948 [student work] (Box 4)
  - Barrier Experiment: Restraint during extincton - Bursary students, 1950-51 [student work], 1950-1951 (Box 4)
  - Bursary Students: Habit Strength as a Function of Number of Trials - Spring 1950 (Box 4)
  - Bower, Gordon - Plots of Reward and Nonreward Points [student work] (Box 4)
  - Choy, M. and Levine, J. - Hunger/Thirst/Reward Schedules [student work], 1956 (Box 4)
  - Comments on Rosenblum and Harlow [NEM article], 1963 (Box 4)
  - Auld: Psychotherapy, first session with Mrs. Blake [student work], 1950 (Box 4)
  - Baldwin, Janet Claire - Summer Experiment 1952 [student work] (Box 5)
  - NY Academy of Sciences: Conference 1954 - NEM: Regulation of Hunger and Appetite, Shortcomings of Food Consumption (Box 5)
  - Faust - Miller - Habituation to Stress; Unpublished ms. (Box 5)
  - Central Stimulation and other New Approaches to Motivation and Reward - NEM 1957 (Box 5)
  - Influence of Place of Punishment on Conflict - NEM paper for EPA 1939 (Box 5)
  - Pharmacology Manuscript - Drawings, etc., 1959 (Box 5)
  - American Psychologist - Subliminal Advertising (Box 5)
  - Jensen, Donald - Appetitive Conditioning - Oral Fistula [student work] (Box 5)
  - Saccharine Notes, references, plans for further experiments - Miller et al., 1958, 1958-1963 (Box 5)
  - Conflict Lecture - Recorded on Soundscriber Records (Box 5)
  - Miller and Koch Ms. 1958 - S-R Conflict, Project A (Box 5)
  - Pavlovian Conference Talk - Integration of neurophysiological and behavioral research, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - APA 1960 - Conflict Behavior and Drugs (Box 5)
  - Tetanus Toxin (Box 5)
  - Titration Apparatus (notes left by Herbert Barry) (Box 5)
  - Tongue Lick Amplifier and Recording, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - Socialization - Joint project [NEM and John Dollard], 1940 (Box 5)
  - Personality and Psychotherapy - Reviews, 1951-1953 (Box 5)
  - Objective Questions on Personality and Psychotherapy, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Personality and Psychotherapy [Correspondence - incl. letters from B.F. Skinner, Lewis Terman, Carl Rogers, Kenneth Spence, etc.], 1950 (Box 5)
  - Dollard, Ms: on Collaborative Thinking, 1948 (Box 5)
  - Dollard, Ms: The Acquisition of New Social Habits (Box 5)
  - "From Picture to Brain" [prepared for Eastman Kodak Company By NEM and J. Dollard] (Box 5)
  - Outline of "Some Applications of Learning Theory to Psychotherapy", 1950 (Box 5)
  - Fear and Anxiety [Notes on - info on experts] (Box 5)
  - Films: Behavioral Biology, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
  - Foundations' Fund [for Research in Psychiatry] - Minutes of meetings 1959, 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - FFRP [Foundations' Fund for Research in Psychiatry] - Meeting Jan. 20, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Gifts - AandS - Ford Foundation (Miller), 1957 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation - Child Development, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Ford [Motor Company] Reports - Dollard [On buying cars], 1964 (Box 5)
  - Fullbright Awards, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - NHLBI [Natl. Heart, Lung and Blood Institute] Conference on Cardiovascular Instrumentation, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - NHLI [National Heart and Lung Institute, NIH], 1976 (Box 5)
  - NHLI [National Heart and Lung Institute Conference] May 11-12, 1975 (Box 5)
  - NIMH - Lasky, J.- Correspondence re site visits, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
  - NIMH Minority Research Workshop III, 1977 (Box 5)
  - NIMH - Schwartz Site Visit, 2/2/79, 1979 (Box 5)
  - NMHA [National Mental Health Association] - Research Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - National Mental Health Association, 1981 (Box 5)
  - NMHA [National Mental Health Association] - Research Committee - 1982 (Box 5)
  - National Science Foundation, 1982 (Box 6)
  - N.Y. Academy of Sciences, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - N.Y. Academy of Sciences - Sechzer Committee [Animal Research], 1984 (Box 6)
  - NY State Department Of Education, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Obese Rats, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Peace Research - Life Sciences, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Wolper Productions - March of Time (Irwin Rosten, producer), 1965 (Box 6)
  - Peace Corps [narrative account of start of Peace Corps and telegram to NEM to participate in planning], 1961 (Box 6)
  - Pavlovian Conference on Higher Nervous Activity, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
  - Pavlovian Society, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Penicillin - for seizures (Box 6)
  - Pennsylvania, University of - Board of Physical and Biological Sciences, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Physiological Psychology Seminars, 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Pittsburgh, University of - Project Talent Office Bulletins, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Placebo Effects for Blood Pressure (Box 6)
  - Polio [NEM Chairman of Jackson Lab Board of Scientific Overseers], 1971 (Box 6)
  - Portable Monitor [Biofeedback], 1981 (Box 6)
  - President's Biomedical Research Panel - Overview Cluster, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Psychological Corporation, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Psychiatry, World Congress of - IV [Madrid, 1966 - on Higher Nervous Activity] (Box 6)
  - Psychiatry, World Congress of - Montreal, 1961 (Box 6)
  - Psychonomic Society, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Psychopharmacology - General Matters, 1960 (Box 6)
  - Rats: Curare, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Rats: Strain Differences, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Rats, Wild, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Replication Inquiries, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Replication Problems (Box 6)
  - Replications in Psychology - Education Board, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Research Corporation, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Research Foundation - Mental Hygiene, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Research Funding, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Research Problems '81, 1981 (Box 6)
  - RDB [Research and Development Board] - Report of Working Group, 1951 (Box 6)
  - San Francisco - Food and Civilization, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Schizophrenia - references, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Science- Editorial Board, 1962-1985 (Box 6)
  - Science Education, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Sigma Xi - Grants-in-Aid (Box 6)
  - Silliman Lectures, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - Society of Behavioral Medicine, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
  - Society of Experimental Psychologists [SEP]1959, 1958-1965 (Box 7)
  - SEP 1968, 1968-1984 (Box 7)
  - Springer Series [Behavioral Therapy and Medicine], 1980 (Box 7)
  - Sterling-Winthrop Research Inst. [Dr. Tainter], 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1951 (Box 7)
  - RDB [Research and Development Board, Department of Defense, Working Group For Study of Human Behavior] - Editorial criticism, letter to McDowell, 1951 (Box 7)
  - RDB Appointment and Pay Data, 1951-1953 (Box 7)
  - Taylor, Donald W. - Colorado Seminar, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Television Research 1964, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Texas U. At Houston - Advisory Council 1965, 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Thermal Shuttle - Morphine Data (Box 7)
  - Totus Homo [Italian Journal], 1970-1977 (Box 7)
  - University for Peace [U.N.], 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Finland - Leningrad, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Miller, N.E. - Some Experiments on the Mechanisms of Motivation [NEM paper give in Russia and translated, printed in Russian journal], 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - US/USSR Scientific Exchange on Hypertension '83, 1983-1987 (Box 7)
  - USSR Emigres [Khanukayev], 1982 (Box 7)
  - Alpha Refs (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning - Clinical Cases of Possible Relevance, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Constipation - Henry Erle et al., 1970 (Box 7)
  - Egg Project Proposal, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Emphysema, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Epilepsy, 1968 (Box 7)
  - Gastrointestinal - GI Project Proposal, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Protection of Human Subjects, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Headaches, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Heart Rate - Miller and Solomon, 1967, 1967-1973 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension - Greenspan, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Blood Pressure - Dupont, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Blood Pressure Monitor - Description - B. Dworkin Design, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension, Human, 1969-1973 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension - Hypothesis, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension Protocol - 1972 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension - US/USSR Exchange, 1983 (Box 7)
  - Hypertension - Portable Recorder, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Hypnosis, 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Human Experimentation, Committee of Ethics - Correspondence with Chmn., J. Hirsch at Rockefeller [Projects from NEM's laboratory], 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Institutional Review Board [Rockefeller], 1976-1984 (Box 7)
  - Parkinson's, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Polio Patients, 1970-1974 (Box 7)
  - Possible Collaborators, 1969-1975 (Box 7)
  - Raynaud's Syndrome, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Stomach, 1971-1973 (Box 7)
  - Temperature, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Tinnitus, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning Horrors! [newsclips], 1981 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning - Decline in Effects on Rats, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning - Publicity, 1969-1976 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning Research - Smithsonian Science Info Exchange, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning Publicity and responses - 1969, 1969-1976 (Box 7)
  - Volunteer Patients, 1969-1980 (Box 7)
  - Refs for Visceral Neurophysiology, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Visceral Learning, 1967-1972 (Box 7)
  - Center for the Study and Reduction of Violence at UCLA [Proposed research program], 1973-1974 (Box 7)
  - WNET-13 [Series of T.V. programs on the brain and the mind - NEM asked to advise], 1978 (Box 7)
  - President's Science Advisory Committee [PSAC]
    - Life Sciences Panel - NEM, chair of Behavioral Sciences Subpanel, which produced report "Strengthening the Behavioral Sciences," - FINAL DRAFT, 4/20/62 [Pub. in Science mag., on that date and 10,000 copies mailed out from Govt. Printing Office 2-3 weeks later], 1962 (Box 8)